A Finding Aid to the Howard Wise Gallery Records, 1943-1989, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Exhibition Files, 1957-1968; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 6-7
  - Peter Sedgley (New York, Oct. 11-29, 1966), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Gunther Uecker (New York, Nov. 1-19, 1966), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Lowell Nesbitt: Interior Spaces (New York, Nov. 22-Dec. 10, 1968), 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Earl Reiback, A Festival of Light (New York, Dec. 13, 1966-Jan. 7, 1967), 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Recent Works by George Ortman (New York, Jan. 10-28, 1967), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Lights in Orbit (New York, Feb. 4-March 4, 1967), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Julio Le Parc (New York, March 11-April 1, 1967), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Takis: Magnetic Sculpture (New York, April 7-29, 1967), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Charles Mattox: Kinetic Sculpture; and Fluorescent Painting by Herbert Aach (New York, May 9-June 3, 1967), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Marta Minuhin's Minuphone Booth (New York, June 27-July 28, 1967), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - The Paintings of George McNeil (New York, Sept. 19-Oct. 7, 1967), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Billy Apple's U.F.O.'s (Unidentified Fluorescent Objects) (New York, Nov. 11-Dec. 2, 1967), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Festival of Lights (New York, Dec. 9, 1967-Jan. 6, 1968), 1967-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - George Ortman (New York, Jan. 13-Feb. 3, 1968), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Hans Haacke (New York, Jan. 13-Feb. 3, 1968), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Earl Reiback (New York, Feb. 10-March 11, 1968), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Howard Jones (New York, March 9-30, 1968), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Thomas Wilfred's Lumia Composition, "Cuccata Opus 162 in Three Movements" (New York, March 1968), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Tony Martin's Game Room and "Invironment" (New York, April 6-May 4, 1968), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Tsai: Cybernetic Sculpture (New York, May 11-June 1, 1968), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Summer Lights (New York, [?]-July 26, 1968), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Niizuma: Stone and Canvas Sculptures (New York, Oct. 5-25, 1968), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Tom Lloyd: Kinetic Light Sculptures (New York, Nov. 2-23, 1968), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Fun on 57th Street (New York, Nov. 30-Dec. 31, 1968), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 37)
- Business Records, 1957-1989; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 2.6 Linear feet Boxes 7-9
  Cash disbursements are mainly for Howard Wise's travel and entertainment expenses. Memoranda and correspondence between Cleveland and New York Galleries include debit and credit memoranda and concern sales, inventory, and shipments.
  The notebooks (64 small pocket volumes) contain brief notes on paintings, names and addresses, appointments and schedules, reminders, and a few lecture notes. Sales records consist of accounts paid, arranged by purchaser, and copies of sales receipts arranged chronologically. Slides consist of approximately 800 images of artworks and installation views.
  A number of records pertain to the management of Howard Wise's personal art collection and date to the period following the closure of the Howard Wise Gallery. Records related to loans document loans of works by George McNeil, including correspondence with McNeil, and Jan Muller.
  - Addresses, 1957, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Appointment Calendar, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Art Purchases, Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
    - Europe, 1957-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 40-42)
    - United States, 1956-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Artists Affiliated with Howard Wise Gallery (lists), 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Balance Sheet, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Bank Reconciliation, 1960, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Budget, Promotion, 1958-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Cash Disbursements, 1957-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 48-52)
  - Employees, 1959-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Exhibition Schedules, 1964-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - "Gallery Notes" (newsletter of Howard Wise Gallery of Present Day Painting and Sculpture), 1959-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Inventories and Consignments, 1958-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Lists of Artworks at Residences, 1982-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Loans, Archival Resource Key
    - George McNeil, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Jan Müller, 1984-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Memoranda and Correspondence between Cleveland and New York Galleries, 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Notebooks, 1957-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 61-64)
  - Notes regarding Consignments, Loans, Sales, 1959-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Paid Bills (Cleveland), 1956-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 2-13)
  - Paid Bills (New York), Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 14-26)
    Abbey, 1963-1968
    Alpha, 1960-1965
    Art-Cart, 1963-1964
    Circle Foto, 1964-1968
    Clark, Fred, 1960-1965
    Con Edison, 1966-1968
    Frank's Hardware, 1965-1969
    Ginnever, Chuck, 1960-1963
    Holmes Electric Protective Co., 1960-1968
    New York Telephone, 1965-1968
    Pauley, Hal, 1964-1967
    Schlemowitz, Abram, 1961-1963
    Thorn's Transfer, 1962
  - Personal Business Records, 1984-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 27)
    Includes travel itineraries and a certificate from the Union of Concerned Scientists
  - Photographs - Howard Wise Gallery of Present Day Painting and Sculpture, Cleveland (interior and exterior views), 1957-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Press Releases, 1961-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Rental Plan ("Art for the Home"), Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
    - Completed Agreements, 1958-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - General Information and Sample Contracts, circa 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Gallery Artists, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Sales Records, Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
    - Accounts Paid (A-R, by client), 1957-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 33-38)
    - Accounts Paid (S-Z, by client), 1957-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    - Receipts, 1957-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 3-7)
  - Slides of Artworks and Installations, circa 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 8-15)
- Writings, 1957-1984; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 9
  Writings consist of essays and speeches by Howard Wise, writings on Howard Wise and the Howard Wise Gallery artists by Douglas MacAgy and Marita Sturken, and a typescript recollection of a dinner party conversation with Supreme Court Justice Warren Burger from 1973.
  - Essays and Speeches by Howard Wise, 1960-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Notes on a Conversation betwen Howard Wise and Supreme Court Justice Burger, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - "Vox Pop" by Douglas MacAgy, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Writings about Howard Wise by Marita Sturken, 1983-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Video Recordings, 1973 - circa 1985; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 2.5 Linear feet Boxes 9-12
  Arrangement
  Video recordings are arranged alphabetically by name for videos whose dominant subject is an individual, followed by videos documenting events in chronological order. Moving image material created by others is arranged at the end of the series.
  Series contains video footage shot by Howard Wise, mainly of interviews with artists in Wellfleet, Mass. and other Cape Cod locations. Most of the video recordings by Wise contain raw, unedited footage, and individual tapes may contain more than one subject. A video log book containing notes on many of the videos lists additional subjects for each tape, with page numbers corresponding to numbers on tapes. Many tapes also have detailed labels. A few of the interviews seem to have been edited later into a series Wise called "Video Portraits," including intervies with Serge Chermeyeff, Edwin Dickinson, and Jack Tworkov. A printed program for a public screening of these works, called "Video Capers" is found at the beginning of the series. Note that not all of the subjects listed in the program are represented in the extant footage. An interview with Howard Wise is also found. Interviews are on 21 videoreels (1/2") and 4 videocassettes (U-matic)
  In addition to interviews, events such as art openings, benefits, gallery tours, local camp activities are documented in the recordings. A dinner party with Jean Dubuffet and Thomas Messer, as well as footage of the premiere performance of Dubuffet's Coucou Bazaar at the Guggenheim Museum, are also found. Recordings of panel discussions held on board an ocean liner, mostly on science subjects, are also found. Events are on 12 videoreels (1/2").
  Footage of kinetic, media, and performance artworks includes multiple works from the 1967 Lights in Orbit exhibition and Nam June Paik at Bonino Gallery on 1 videocassette (VHS), multiple Howard Wise Gallery exhibitions from 1964-1965 on two videocassettes (U-matic), including On the Move (1964), Group Zero (1964), Gerald Oster, and Len Lye's Bounding Steel Sculptures (1965). Also found is a video performance by Hannah Wilke labeled "Noh Film" on 1 video reel.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Many of the video recordings in this series have been digitized for research access.
  - Program for "Video Capers" Event, circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Video Log Book, 1973-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Marcel Breuer, 1973-1974; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Serge Chermeyeff, 1973-1974; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Label reads "Video portrait of Serge Chermayeff 1973-1974 by Howard Wise"; 3 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
  - Edwin Dickinson, 1973; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Label reads "Edwin Dickinson: Video Portrait"; 1 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Ethel Edwards, 1973; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videoreels (1/2 inch) Label reads "Video Capers - art opening Ethel Edwards, Xavier Gonzalez in his Wellfleet Studio" diameter 7 inch; 3 Videoreels (1/2 inch) diameter 5 inch (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
  - Xavier Gonzales, 1973; Archival Resource Key; 3 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 10, Folder 7-8)
  - Marty and Jack Hall, 1973; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 10, Folder 9, Item 1)
  - Al Jensen, 1973; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 10, Folder 9, Item 2)
  - Juliet Kepes, 1973; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 10, Folder 10, Item 1)
  - Gyorgy Kepes, 1976; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 10, Folder 10, Item 2)
  - Robert Jay Lifton, 1973; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 11, Folder 1, Item 1)
  - Sidney Simon, 1973; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 11, Folder 1, Item 2)
  - Lilli Saarinen, 1973; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Jack Tworkov, 1974; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Howard Wise, 1980; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Label reads "H.W. on Art" (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Dinner Party with Jean Dubuffet, Thomas Messer, and Others, 1973; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Panel Discussions on the S.S. Canberra, 1973; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Wellfleet Terns, 1973; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 11, Folder 7, Item 1)
  - Wellfleet Bay Wildlife Sanctuary Camp, 1973; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 11, Folder 7, Item 2)
  - Tour of Left Bank and Cove Galleries, Wellfleet, Mass., 1973; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 11, Folder 8, Item 1)
  - Truro Invitational Tennis Tournament, 1975; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videoreels (1/2 inch) Label reads "Lee Falk Tennis Party" (Box 11, Folder 8, Item 2)
  - Castle Hill Art School Benefit and Interviews at Cape Cod Galleries, 1973; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Shown are Cherry Stone and Kendall Galleries.
  - Coucou Bazaar, 1973; Archival Resource Key; 3 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 11, Folder 10-11)
    Premiere performance at the opening of Jean Dubuffet retrospective at the Guggenheim Museum.
  - Works from Lights in Orbit Exhibition (1967), circa 1985; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Video copy of film not found with collection (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Footage (1964-1965), circa 1980; Archival Resource Key; 2 Videocassettes (U-matic) Video is copy of film and other footage not found with collection. Labels read: "On the Move, Group Zero, Oster Exhibition, Len Lye's Bounding Sculptures" (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Hannah Wilke, Noh Film, 1974; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videoreels (1/2 inch) (Box 12, Folder 3)